<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://erikhartman.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://erikhartman.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-21T11:08:12+00:00</updated><id>https://erikhartman.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>My personal website. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The broken game of academic research: how journals are shifting the incentives of researchers and ruining science</title><link href="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2024/game-theory-academics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The broken game of academic research: how journals are shifting the incentives of researchers and ruining science"/><published>2024-03-27T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-27T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2024/game-theory-academics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2024/game-theory-academics/"><![CDATA[<p>Games are fundamental to the behavior of rational agents, and many biological, societal, and economic systems can be understood and analyzed using game theory. In game theory, a game is defined by a set of players, a set of rules, and a set of objectives. In large, the goal of game theory is to define and study games, and in doing so, it can help to define policies (rules) and actions that optimize the process of reaching an objective. Life itself can be construed as the most elemental of games, where living organisms are the players striving to survive, thrive, and procreating. Similarly, conflicts such as wars can be analyzed as strategic games, with goals like territorial conquest or population control. Naturally, tactics become important in games, and a large part of game theoretic endeavors lies in identifying the optimal tactics (actions) that result in the desired outcome of a game.</p> <p>When breaking down a complex system into a set of games, it becomes possible to define policies that shift the incentives of players to favor a desired outcome. Here, I propose an exploration into the academic sphere as a set of games, illustrating how the misalignment of incentives and goals among key stakeholders has led to suboptimal outcomes that fail to serve the interests of humanity.</p> <h2 id="the-game-of-academia">The game of academia</h2> <p>In academia and research, a familiar game unfolds, involving two primary players: researchers and the public, who are the ultimate beneficiaries. The overarching objectives of this game are twofold: to expand humanity’s understanding of the universe and its phenomena, and to propel technological advancements in ways that benefits humanity. To steer clear of moral and ethical debates, the notion of “benefitting humanity” is defined as the ethically optimal objective in a Platonic sense (which may also include benefitting other organisms). Ideally, the academic system should incentivize actions aligned with these objectives, fostering beneficial research, facilitating the dissemination of knowledge, and fostering technological innovation.</p> <p>Adopting a game theoretic viewpoint to navigate our intricate reality necessitates acknowledging that individuals are often enmeshed in multiple simultaneous games, each characterized by potentially conflicting objectives. Researchers are human too, and harbor ambitions beyond the altruistic pursuit of knowledge. Alongside the noble aspirations outlined earlier, they are driven by more egoistic aims such as financial security and the acquisition of influence and power. Most researchers therefore also strive for academic fame, which is accompanied by a larger paycheck and greater influence. The researcher now has three goals: the two ideal ones mentioned in the previous section and to become a famous researcher.</p> <p>Fame in academia is a product of recognition and esteem bestowed by both the public and one’s peers. In essence, if the broader public perceives an individual as prominent within their field, then they indeed attain fame. If we wish to keep the researcher’s goals aligned with the ideal goals, it is therefore pertinent that the public and peers share these goals. Moreover, it’s crucial that the public receives an impartial portrayal of the published research, thereby facilitating an unbiased evaluation of the researchers contributions. We have now introduced a new player into the game, namely the communicator between the researcher, their peers, and the public. In actuality, the communicators are the scientific journals.</p> <p>The power journals hold in academia is that of selecting and spreading research findings. They therefore play an important part in furthering and extending the border of knowledge, but they also play a large role in governing the influence and fame of researchers. It is therefore crucial that journals uphold a level of integrity and that they are regulated so that they don’t sway from the goal of science and placate the egoistic needs of humans. Unfortunately, this is exactly what is currently happening in the field of academia.</p> <p>Journals are highly efficient profit machines that dictate the success of researchers while exploiting their flaws as humans as well as their institutions for monetary gain. They play their own game, in which impact factors are a proxy for profit, and their tactics include utilising researchers as editors, reviewers, and publishers, creating a money-printing cycle where researchers run like hamsters in the pursuit of scientific glory.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/running_man-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/running_man-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/running_man-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/running_man.jpg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>As long as the publication system exists in its current state, there will always be a misalignment between the ideal goals and the incentives of the researchers. This results in bad research, where the goal is to publish in high-impact journals instead of doing good science, resulting in reporting bias, fraud, and hype trains. Although the downstream impact of such research is unclear, it is reasonable to believe that research without such systems in place would generate better science, which in turn would make the world a better place. The diversion from such a world is morally wrong.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/utopia_dystopia-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/utopia_dystopia-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/utopia_dystopia-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/utopia_dystopia.jpg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="how-to-align-incentives-with-goals">How to align incentives with goals</h2> <p>While it is possible to imagine a scenario where the researchers are unaffected by the incentives of journals and uphold a moral standard that furthers the ideal goals of research, it seems like a highly unlikely one. This is because of the inherent imbalance within the system, wherein any deviation from this ideal stance instantly elevates the errant researcher to fame, disrupting the equilibrium of the game. It is not a steady equilibrium. It is therefore necessary to change the system to align the incentives with the ideal goals, which means altering the way in which research is evaluated and spread to the public and to peers.</p> <p>But how can science be spread in an unbiased way that doesn’t incentivize the researchers to deviate from the desired outcome? This is a difficult question for which I have no definitive answer. However, two pragmatic actions, advocated by numerous voices in the academic community, stand out as compelling avenues for enhancing the publishing system:</p> <ol> <li> <p>Transition away from traditional journals and pre-publication peer review models toward embracing pre-print servers. These platforms would entail an initial screening to filter out blatantly flawed submissions, while allowing the bulk of research to be freely accessible without undue editorial influence.</p> </li> <li> <p>Embrace transparency by implementing open post-publication peer review.</p> </li> </ol> <p>These actions would remove monetization from the publication system, reduce the time of publication, thereby increase the rate of scientific exchange, and reduce the level of gatekeeping currently upheld by monopolized publishing companies. Journals play an important role in identifying good research, but this can be done just as easily with post-publication peer review and other types of archives.</p> <p>This model has already been adopted by some fields of research, prominently in machine learning (ML) research. Here, articles are often never published in any conventional peer reviewed journal, but instead servers like arXiv are the names of the game. Papers deemed noteworthy quickly gain traction and virality within the research community. Alternative decentralized ways of funding, doing, and reporting science utilizing the Web3 stack are on the rise. Referred to as DeSci (Decentralized Science), these alternative frameworks represent a potential avenue for reshaping the scientific enterprise. However, their widespread adoption remains uncertain. In general, I believe that the two points above are enough to fix the problems with journals. Further, they are actionable and available with current technology.</p> <h2 id="in-summary">In summary</h2> <p>While acknowledging the valuable contributions of scientific journals, it’s essential to address a fundamental issue: the disconnect between researchers’ incentives and the overarching goals of scientific advancement. When publications are valued primarily for their placement in prestigious journals and their impact on authors’ h-indexes, rather than for their substantive content and contributions to their respective fields, it undermines the integrity of scientific research. In an era where the importance of science and technology has never been greater, we must recognize the imperative for change within academic norms. Only by reforming the current system can we ensure that scientific endeavors truly serve the greater good.</p>]]></content><author><name>Erik Hartman</name></author><category term="game"/><category term="theory"/><category term="academia"/><category term="publishing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[the flawed academic system through the lens of game theory]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Writing academic articles in Markdown</title><link href="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2024/markdown/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing academic articles in Markdown"/><published>2024-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2024/markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2024/markdown/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>TLDR:</strong> I write my papers in Markdown using:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://shd101wyy.github.io/markdown-preview-enhanced/#/">Markdown Preview Enhanced in VS Code</a></li> <li><a href="https://pandoc.org/">Pandoc</a> to export to any format (Word/PDF in my cases).</li> <li><a href="https://github.com/pandoc/lua-filters">lua-filters</a> and .tex-templates to stylize the documents</li> </ul> <p>It’s really nice. Here are some more extensive articles / videos about writing academic papers in markdown which uses a similar workflow to mine:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://jaantollander.com/post/scientific-writing-with-markdown/">This article by Jaan Tollander is really all you need.</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J86Pm62XM_Q">Extensive video by Shaping Openness.</a></li> <li><a href="https://brainbaking.com/post/2021/02/writing-academic-papers-in-markdown/">Shorter article by BrainBaking.</a></li> </ul> <hr/> <p>I’ve been on the search for a lightweight and reliable way to write academic articles, but it’s more difficult than you’d think. Today, the gold standards are LaTeX (for math, physics and engineering) and Word for basically everything else. While both of these tools are good, they’re lacking in several aspects.</p> <p>Word has too much functionality. For scientific articles, all you really need is the abilities to:</p> <ol> <li>create headers</li> <li>insert figures</li> <li>insert tables</li> <li>write mathematical expressions/chemical formulae etc.</li> <li>reference and cite</li> </ol> <p>Beyond this, Word offers a bunch of things which really is just bloat, like different fonts, shapes, colors, etc. It also is severely lacking in points 4 and 5. Also, it uses the .docx-format, which is impossible to read without using Word.</p> <p>LaTeX is way better in points 4 and 5, as writing mathematical expressions and referencing using .bib is extremely easy. It also cuts down on the bloat. However, it has a bit of a learning curve, is a pain to set up and has several quirks that you have to get used to. You can skip the setup by using Overleaf, but then you restrict your writing to when having internet access, and you’re relying on Overleaf servers.</p> <p>In the end, I’ve settled on writing in pure <strong>Markdown</strong> and use a set of tools to get everything you need to write scientific articles. I keep my paper-files in a subdirectory in the .git-repo for my project, so that everything is kept in .git and is in the same place. I then use Markdown Preview Enhanced and Pandoc to generate the desired formats.</p> <h2 id="what-is-markdown">What is Markdown</h2> <p>Markdown is a lightweight markup language that uses plain text formatting syntax to create structured documents. Here are some basic examples of Markdown syntax:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Headers:
# Heading 1
## Heading 2
### Heading 3

Emphasis:
*italic* or _italic_
**bold** or __bold__

Lists:
- Item 1
- Item 2
  - Subitem 2.1
  - Subitem 2.2
1. Numbered item 1
2. Numbered item 2

Links:
[Link text](http://example.com)

Images:
![Alt text](image.jpg)

Code:
`inline code`
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="markdown-preview-enhanced">Markdown Preview Enhanced</h2> <p><em>*This requires Visual Studio Code</em></p> <p><a href="https://shd101wyy.github.io/markdown-preview-enhanced/#/">Markdown Preview Enhanced</a> is an extension available in Visual Studio Code that allows you to preview your Markdown-files while writing them. It also supports Mathematical expressions in a LaTeX-style. Writing in your code editor allows you to easily check your code for results and then quickly add them to your paper. In general, this creates the best writing experience I’ve had.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/MPE-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/MPE-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/MPE-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/MPE.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Example of how your VS Code may look when writing markdown in Markdown Preview Enhanced. </div> <h2 id="converting-to-html-tex-pdf-docx-using-pandoc">Converting to .html, .tex, .pdf, .docx using Pandoc</h2> <p>The magic sets in when you combine Markdown Preview Enhanced with <a href="https://pandoc.org/">Pandoc</a>. Pandoc is a versatile document converter and markup language processor that allows for the conversion between different document formats, and it integrates with Markdown Preview Enhanced.</p> <p>By specifying arguments in the YAML-header of your document (see below), you can export your .md file to many other formats. I’ve used it for creating .docx and .pdf-files, and in both cases it has created well-stylized files.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/md_pdf-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/md_pdf-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/md_pdf-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/md_pdf.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/md_word-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/md_word-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/md_word-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/md_word.png" class="img-fluid z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Example of a document written in markdown and then converted to pdf (via LaTeX) and Word. </div> <h3 id="the-yaml-header">The YAML-header</h3> <p>To convert the file, you need to declare some properties the header of your markdown file. The header sits at the top of the file, and may look like this:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>---
title: My title
institute:
  - lu: Lund University
  - ki: Karolinska institutet
author: 
    - Erik Hartman
        institute: lu
    - Author nr2
        institute: ki
    - etc...
output:
  word_document:
    path: /paper/main.docx
    pandoc_args: ["..."] # some pandoc args
citeproc: true
export_on_save:
  pandoc: true
bibliography: bibliography.bib
csl: vancouver.csl
---
</code></pre></div></div> <p>I use lua-filters to create the author-list. To add these, copy the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">author-info-blocks.lua</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">scholarly-metadata.lua</code> from <a href="https://github.com/pandoc/lua-filters">here</a> and then insert the following to your pandoc_args:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>pandoc_args: ["--lua-filter=scholarly-metadata.lua","--lua-filter=author-info-blocks.lua"]
</code></pre></div></div> <p>More information about using Pandoc with Markdown Preview enhanced can be found <a href="https://shd101wyy.github.io/markdown-preview-enhanced/#/">here</a>.</p> <p>There are a bunch more extensions and plug-ins that you can add if you wish, but what I outline above is really all you need for most purposes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="markdown"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a short tutorial]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Synthetic biology; playing God, life or machine, bioterrorism and biotechnological singularities - a reason for urgency</title><link href="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2020/sb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Synthetic biology; playing God, life or machine, bioterrorism and biotechnological singularities - a reason for urgency"/><published>2020-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2020/sb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2020/sb/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This was written in 2021 for an organization I created called Synthetics.</em></p> <h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3> <p>Progress in biotechnology, synthetic biology and genetic engineering has pressed on into the modern era at an unfathomable pace, tantamount to the progress in computing (https://www.technologyreview.com/s/417628/a-moores-law-for-genetics/). It has surmounted in great achievements and the overcoming of tremendous challenges, although its use has been heavily restricted due to laws and regulations. These restrictions were a response to the surge of biotechnical advancement in the late 20th century, where too little time was spent investigating the consequences of state-of-the-art remedies, mostly in gene-therapy (https://geneticliteracyproject.org/2016/10/07/early-setbacks-gene-therapys-comeback-nearly-complete/) .</p> <p>Recent development in gene-editing has provided a new stomping ground for biotechnology to roam, resulting in local and global DIY-biohacking communities such as iGEM (https://igem.org/Main_Page). Exponential development within the fields has produced new methods of genetically engineering microbes, animals and plants, unlocking the gate for new applications, hitherto unknown organisms, and not to forget, a new field of science - synthetic biology. The field of synthetic biology has no generally accepted definition, however, for our purposes, we settle that:</p> <p>“Synthetic biology is the engineering of biology: the synthesis of complex, biologically based (or inspired) systems, which display functions that do not exist in nature. This engineering perspective may be applied at all levels of the hierarchy of biological structures—from individual molecules to whole cells, tissues and organisms. In essence, synthetic biology will enable the design of ‘biological systems’ in a rational and systematic way” (Synthetic Biology: Applying Engineering to Biology: Report of a NEST High Level Expert Group).</p> <p>It has become clear that the perceived sanctity of the blueprint of life - our genome, has been disturbed, and once we’ve fundamentally understood the genome of prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells and established standardized ways to edit them, it will dissipate. The recipe for life created by millions of years of evolution through natural selection will lay open to our interpretation and judgement, waiting to be improved. Practiced justly, synthetic biology and genetic engineering may solve many of the current global issues such as environmental deterioration, antibiotic resistance, and lack of global welfare - an opportunity we cannot afford to pass (frankly, one that would be unethical to pass) (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6692427/). Practiced maliciously, it may result in the abrupt demise of mankind. Needless to say, discriminating between these two outcomes should be seen as imperative and the time we spend on figuring out the contributing factors to either fallout is indispensable, yet the field isn’t receiving the attention it deserves in the public eye (Google searches for “AI ethics” and “Biotechnology ethics” receives 384 000 and 24 600 hits respectively).</p> <h3 id="ai-similarities">AI similarities</h3> <p>A similar field of science which has received the attention and ethical consideration it warrants is that of AI, with philosophers and scientists like Nick Bostrom, Max Tegmark, Sam Harris, Daniel Dennett and many more preaching its importance. Today, the field is well developed (it even has its own Wikipedia-page: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethics_of_artificial_intelligence) and has reached a status of importance close to that of nuclear war in academic circles. AI is in its fetal stages of development, the equivalent of a mere eight-celled embryo, and once AI reaches a stage of iterated self-improvement beyond human understanding and control (a so-called singularity), the subsequent ethical considerations are worthless. Due to the explosive progressive nature of AI, philosophers and scientists have had to look decades and centuries into the future to observe and develop ethical inquiries. This has certainly required terrific determination and creativity on their part, and helpful tools have been created to aid their contemplation. I suggest that the progressive nature of AI is in many ways similar to that of biotechnology, an idea I will develop further later, and comparing the two fields may very well guide us in our quest for true north in the realm of bioethics.</p> <p>Natural selection was long the driving force for evolution through a process of trial-and-error. A gene may be randomly mutated, and if its function is impaired, and contributes to its host death, it will be discontinued. Natural selection was then overcome by human ingenuity, and the realization that offspring inherits traits from its parents. This gave way for artificial selection, where traits which were favoured by man were selected for. Today, scientific breakthroughs has broken all speed-records of evolution. By tampering with the genome of microbes, plants, animals and ourselves, we’re no longer limiting selection to certain traits nor are we limiting it to a certain pace. Once genetic enhancement begins in the realm of cognitive improvement, it will revamp our own ability to enhance itself (https://www.pewresearch.org/science/2016/07/26/human-enhancement-the-scientific-and-ethical-dimensions-of-striving-for-perfection/) At the point of view of evolution, living organisms has reached a state of singularity. Similar to how we won’t keep up with the unfathomable progress of an AI who reached the state of iterated self-improvement, natural selection will no longer keep up with us, for we have reached a state of such improvement. The singularity is further emphasized by the innate structure of biological systems and current research in biotechnology. One of the largest obstacles impeding progress today is the difficulty in cutting and pasting genes, and while the emergence of cut-and-paste-techniques like CRISPR-cas9 and prime editing accelerated advancement, both are far from perfect. As of now, there is a registry (iGEM registry https://igem.org/Registry) of 20 000 gene-parts (i.e. BioBricks) developed by researchers , but their use and compatibility is limited. Once universal scissors are created, which we can expect to happen in the 21th century, all combinations of parts and biological chassis will be available to us and the world will face a biotech-splosion - steepening the evolutionary singularity.</p> <p><img src="../img/synthethics-fig1.jpg" alt="fig"/> Figure 1: The rate of evolution has fluctuated over time, but on a long time-scale it’s almost constant. Domestication of animals and crops increased the rate of evolution massively. Once genetic engineering is available, an evolutionary singularity is reached. The rate of evolution is similar to the rate of increase in computing power once iterated self-improvement is reached and when accounting for different timeframes.</p> <p>Why establishing a ethical ground is urgent Since the first living organism was brought into the world, natural selection has caused evolution. It has brought extinction upon those organisms unworthy of survival, and improved those on the brink of extinction. Blindly, it has favoured survival, nothing else. As of late, artificial selection - the trait-selection process made by man to enhance traits already present in plants or livestock, has dominated. As we move into an era of genetic engineering, none of these processes will dominate. Instead, man will be free to pick and choose novel traits, and to directly be the judge of what genes survive and which genes are to be discarded, and it is our responsibility to ensure a moral righteousness in our choices. Genetic modification may give rise to many immoral and riskful ventures, and as presented above, will occur rapidly. Therefore, as we strive towards enhancing microbes, plants, animals or humans, the consequences of our actions are heavily reliant on the moral status quo. There are more risks in need of ethical consideration than are currently regarded in the field of biotechnology, and as showcased above, these are urgent. The field of biotechnology should experience similar preparatory actions as those taken in the field of AI.</p> <h3 id="risk-philosophy">Risk philosophy</h3> <p>Technological advancement inherently brings the opportunity to act against the welfare of intelligent life. We can imagine the culmination of a positive moral outcome to rest on a knife’s edge, with almost all outcomes throwing it off balance. Most technological advancement increases the well-being of humans due to the fact that it counters existing misery, however, as we plug more holes of human hardship through advancement, the odds of producing technology with benefits outweighing the moral risks for malicious intent dwindles. Luckily, we’re far from having plugged all the holes of hardship, and the benefits of technological advancement generally grossly outweigh the entourage of risks. This analogy of steadily diminishing returns soon falls apart due to the large variation in dimensions of risks - if we ever encounter a risk so large that it proves detrimental to intelligent life, it tips the moral outcome too far from the knife’s edge. The implementation of large risks are elegantly exercised in the vulnerable world hypothesis (Bostrom, 2019). Here, all possible innovations, ideas and discoveries lie in an urn, in the form of balls, and the shade of the ball defines its risk for detrimental outcome. So far, we’ve drawn many white balls and only a few grey balls with low to moderate risks associated with them. However, when reaching down into the urn of innovation we’re always running the risk of picking a black ball - one that unfailingly results in the destruction of civilization. Diminishing returns can be implemented into the analogy by stating that the amount of balls in the urn is finite. As we draw a white ball, we subsequently increase the risk of drawing a black ball. When considering the advancement in biotechnology, we must constantly keep in mind the possibility of drawing a black ball, and we must, to the best of our ability, try to predict the shade of the ball before it’s drawn, because once a ball is drawn, it cannot be put back.</p> <h3 id="moral-failure">Moral failure</h3> <p>Moral risks are not as apparent as the ones of technological advancement. An innovation may be spawned from a context which we later recognize to be completely immoral, and we would be unable to determine the shade of the ball until our morality has shifted. Alternatively, an innovation may seem wholesome due to a prolonged immoral effect. This could be the case if an inherently harmless idea or innovation invariably leads to allowance of immoral behaviour which doesn’t align with our original intent. This could result in subsequent ruination as defined by Bostrom (2012): “Humanity reaches technological maturity in a way that gives good future prospects, yet subsequent developments cause the permanent ruination of those prospects.” All scenarios of moral risks can potentially be deterred, or at least marginalized, if we put effort into contemplating the possible scenarios and moral dilemmas we may face in the future, as done in the field of AI. Here, the problem of goal specification is notorious for needing thorough reflection before realisation. If we were to implement an unsound goal into an AI that has reached the point of singularity, the consequences would be disastrous. Prima facie the problem seems non-existent, but as one tries to define a goal it gets exceedingly difficult (imagine ordering an AI to make all humans happier (a seemingly benevolent goal), only to find all humans mindlessly plugged into a serotonin dispenser for eternity). This task faces many obstacles due to the inhuman nature of the receiving end, such as how to formulate a subjective objective in code, but the thought experiment results in dilemmas which are applicable once we face similar problems in the realm of biotechnology. Inter-cultural and inter-societal quarrels about the direction of progress is an issue we face as technology gets global interest, but who gets to decide where to go? This question is beyond the scope of this paper, but we should always keep the possibility of different points of view in the back of our head when contemplating morality. Although disputes complicate the practice of ethics, the moral landscape never changes, as argued by Sam Harris (and others). This implies that there is always an option in a moral quandary which is objectively and indisputably best, and finding this option is the goal of ethics.</p> <h3 id="moral-considerations">Moral considerations</h3> <p>The potential outcomes from development in biotechnology and genetic modifications are concealed from our current knowledge. Whatever the future may bring, we cannot comprehend it at this time due to the vast technological difference and the uncountable number of variations of outcomes. Not only are we unaware of what progress is to be done and which of the possible outcomes we can imagine will become reality but were also inevitably and necessarily completely unaware of most of those outcomes. The number of lifeforms, biological systems and molecules are nearly endlessly diverse - as beautifully showcased on earth by natural selection. To even imagine that we could fathom all future variations, artificially engineered or not, is ignorant. In fact, understanding evolution through genetic modification is far more hopeless than predicting traits selected for with natural or artificial selection, due to the unpredictable interplay between social, cultural and technological factors which affect the direction of progress and the expansion of the phenotypic arsenal. However, by applying general patterns and tendencies of human welfare to the progress of biotechnology one could assert in which direction we should point our nose, although the progress in human welfare would have to be weighed against the risks of technological advancement and the risk of moral failure. In 2011, Thomas Douglas and Julian Savulescu published an article about “Synthetic biology and the ethics of knowledge”, where they identified three concerns which most likely were to rise among bioethicists in the field of synthetic biology:</p> <p>“(1) concerns about ‘playing God’, which have been prominent in closely related areas of science (2) concerns about undermining the distinction between living things and machines, which attracted early attention from ethicists; and (3) concerns about the deliberate misuse of knowledge from synthetic biology”.</p> <p>They deemed (3) in most need of ethical analysis, and argued that (1) and (2) needn’t be subjects to deep contemplation. Disagreeing, I argue that as advancement in synthetic biology and biotechnology progresses, (1) and (2) will entail risk for moral deterioration and require thorough ethical consideration. Below, I begin dealing with the risk of technological advancement (1), to later move on to that of moral failure in (2) and (3) (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3045879/).</p> <p>Misuse of knowledge (3) Bioterrorism and scientific errors are two of the likely events which may culminate in an existential risk. An appropriate definition of existential risk is “one that threatens the premature extinction of Earth-originating intelligent life or the permanent and drastic destruction of its potential for desirable future development” (Bostrom, 2002). Noteworthy, an existential risk doesn’t only include extermination of intelligent life, but also the eradication of any possibility of future development. This would include the presence of a toxic wasteland as produced by nuclear war, but also the risk of pandemic plagues as produce of malicious intent or miscalculations in biotechnology. Miscalculations are not as uncommon as one may think, in fact, humanity has been on the brink of extinction as a consequence of scientific bloopers before. Famously, during the early years of nuclear trials, Edward Teller calculated that there was a small risk that the atomic bomb would ignite the atmosphere, resulting in an instant demolition of earth. The physicists of Los Alamos later realized that this would be highly unlikely. However, if this would have been the case, and the thought wouldn’t have struck Teller, we would all be dead, and we can consider ourselves lucky to not have been ignited 75 years ago. In the realm of biotechnology, an event similar to the Trinity nuclear test has already occurred. In 2011, a group of researchers wanted to showcase how the deadly H5N1-virus (popularly called the bird flu) could mutate to grow highly contagious. They did so by genetically modifying the virus to make it airborne - creating one of the most dangerous viruses known to man. Although the researchers tried to publish their work, the full articles were never released due to safety concerns (phew) (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3953619/ ). This blooper could easily have resulted in the death of a large proportion of our current population.</p> <p>With the near death scenario regarding the H5N1-virus in mind, we can easily envision a scenario where failure to predict or produce the sought-after functions of an altered organism results in peril. As the technical difficulties regarding the altering of genes subside as a result of technological advancement, the risk for mishaps like these grow. Consider what would happen if everyone had the possibility to produce a nuclear weapon in their garage, a scenario I think we’d all like to avoid. The number of crazed lunatics with access to such technology would surely result in the end of civilization as we know it - a black ball in the urn of innovations. It’s merely a luck of the draw that the creation of nuclear weapons require advanced facilities controlled by knowledgeable and trained personnel. One of the goals of biotechnological advancement is to increase the availability for DIY-biohacking and many of these facilities already exist. As a practitioner of synthetic biology who’s been teaching its principles to high-school students, I can assure you that the goal is increasingly attainable. Developing biological systems isn’t hard, it’s new, We can safely assume that if biohacking becomes available to everyone, including the psychotic hyper-paranoid lunatic who thinks the state has bugged his phone, we will face an existential risk. A grey ball could turn black if the requirements for the innovation is lessened and the risk of producing a black ball without appropriate consideration is alarmingly high.</p> <p><img src="../img/synthethics-fig2.jpg" alt="fig"/> Figure 2: If research is left unregulated the likelihood for existential risks by bioterrorism or blunders increases with biotechnological advancement. As we reach the point of complete availability of DIY-biohacking we can ensure ourselves that bioterrorism or scientific blunders will result in an existential risk.</p> <h3 id="life-or-machine-2">Life or machine (2)</h3> <p>Most biotechnological efforts are conducted in the microscopic realm. Although invisible to the naked eye, microbes play an important role in our surroundings as well as in ourselves - their hosts. The effects our symbiotic companions entail are far more diverse than we previously thought, and many are still undiscovered. Coupling this with the fact that microbes are incredibly easy to engineer, and we’ve created a scientist’s playground. Microorganisms are miniature factories, constantly working in accordance with their genome and responding to their environment - which are under our control. Endeavours in synthetic biology are, by using engineering principles, resulting in programmable bacteria and novel proteins, controlled by complex switches which are implemented into their genome through manmade recombination. We’ve just received a malleable, programmable, fundamental and uniquely alive material that has been completely unused although it’s been around us since the origin of life. This opens up a completely new set of tools in the technological arsenal. Drew Endy, one of the founding fathers of synthetic biology stresses the use of biological organisms:</p> <p>“…I’ve got a pinetree in my front yard. It grows pinecones. I let them fall on the ground and throw them away. That’s crazy as an engineer. This is state of the art nanotechnology that manufactures itself every year.” (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8d-g2dDaZpU&amp;t=1954s) But are we mandated to modify living organisms to act as machines, factories, engineered to our benefit? Synthetic microorganisms fall in-between the life/non-life dichotomy, an, in many instances, lawless abode where companies and researchers make their own rules. These living yet lifeless organisms do not fall within our moral circle, and therefore, the life/machine-duality among them doesn’t affect us. However, if the rim of our moral circle expands beyond the world microbes - which some suggest it should (https://www.researchgate.net/publication/42793350_The_rights_of_microbes) - as a result of some scientific and philosophical breakthroughs, we would be victims to a prolonged immoral effect.</p> <h3 id="our-role-as-creators-1">Our role as Creators (1)</h3> <p>As our creative capacity grows within the field of biotechnology, the horizon of impossibility is pushed further away. Soon, modification will be passé, and only a middlehand to Creation - which is a defining constituent to the field of synthetic biology. In fact, such Creation was first conducted in 2010 when a bacterial genome was created from scratch, and inserted into a chassis bacteria - resulting in the first living organism with a completely synthetic genome (https://www.nature.com/news/2010/100520/full/news.2010.253.html). We can only expect that our capacities as Creators will expand. But how should we classify and treat our own Creations? How can we determine if they’re conscious, happy, or miserable? If we were to create a being which experiences terrible misery ever since the moment life is breathed into it, are we morally responsible for such agony? Should we treat the researchers who developed that organism with the same measures we would treat a criminal causing despair to another living being? If we were to measure our moral status quo in the amount of perceived well-being the world contains, a technology allowing for the mass production of miserable beings would be the epitome of moral blunders which would emphasize that (1) is a risk well worth our consideration (https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs11948-012-9353-z). A similar ethical issue is raised within the world of AI. If we were to create conscious artificial intelligence, or mimic the human brain in a computer, we must consider our moral responsibility as Creators (Bostrom, Superintelligence 2014). As we ponder upon our moral obligations as Creators, we realize that it is essential to develop a deeper understanding of consciousness and life itself before we act. Moral responsibility is not only necessary in the extermination of life and the cause of misery - we’ve dealt with such responsibility for a long time and have a rough understanding of our modes of navigation - but also in the spawning and revision of life.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>New technology requires us to look into new rules of play, and when a technology revolves around tampering with biological life, the building blocks to the most sacred thing on earth, such rules have to be established before the game even begins. The game of biotechnology is definitively a game worth playing - the rewards are simply too large to ignore. Passivity is, like action, a decision which demands moral consideration. Further investigation regarding passivity versus action in the realm of biotechnology is required to know for certain whether we should continue our endeavours, however, I’m convinced action would come out victorious in such a debate. Although victorious, not without cost - with great reward comes great risk, and biotechnology is an exceptional case of high-risk technology. It may lead to our demise in an uncountable amount of ways and any skeptic would be hesitant towards our ascent up the mountains in the biotechnological landscape. Yet here we are, walking blindly towards the unknown. The least we can do, and are morally obligated to do, is to remove the blindfold - otherwise our chances of survival are terribly low. Therefore, we must engage in more serious risk-management regarding the spreading of biotechnological weapons, but we must also ponder upon how to conduct progress in a moral manner.</p> <p>Biological weapons are not the only threat we face, but one amongst many. During technological and moral advancement the seemingly simple questions have difficult answers. By playing God and by not differentiating between simple life and machines we run the risk of facing the worst moral deterioration possible. Technologies like AI and biotechnology are very similar in that they place responsibility in the hands of researchers and scientists and that they’re explosive in nature. This increases the risk for mishap and blunders. Luckily, organisations such as The Future of Life Institute and the Future of Humanity Institute are investigating which way to point our nose. Such progress is rapid in the field of AI, but the field of bioethics is currently underdeveloped. As we orient ourselves in the realm of bioethics we must pose questions like these, otherwise we might end up facing global catastrophe. Finding the true north is paramount to our survival and moral ground.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="synthetic"/><category term="biology"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a longer article for SynthEthics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Brief History of Probiotics</title><link href="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/probiotics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Brief History of Probiotics"/><published>2019-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/probiotics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/probiotics/"><![CDATA[<p>Probiotics, an emerging field of medicine, has been praised and condemned by both experts and the public. It concerns the microorganisms interacting with you, their host, and the possible health benefits they may provide for you. As new research looms, we’re more and more certain that microbes cooperate with us in several ways. Perhaps we are the ones cooperating with them. After all, they were here before us.</p> <p>The host-microbe interaction was first discovered by Antonie van Leeuwenhoek, a 17th-century working-man from Delft. Van Leeuwenhoek’s meticulous artistry enabled him to produce refined lenses, allowing for the observation of microbes. Doing so, a whole new world opened up for the scientific community at the time. Biologist who had only been interested in the macro and comparatively colossal world of mammals and insects were now delving into the world of the miniscule. This was the beginning of the microbial era.</p> <h2 id="symbiotic-evolution">Symbiotic Evolution</h2> <p>The common viewpoint has long been that the microbes have adapted to us. We developed an intestinal tract and they inhabited it. However, this anthropocentric assumption can easily be rebutted by applying the simple statement: they were here before us. It would then seem illogical and unsatisfactory to believe that we developed an intestinal tract and they inhabited it. Instead, it would now seem obvious that a symbiotic and interdependent relationship developed and perhaps even with the microbes in the lead, we constructed an intestinal tract for them to inhabit. We evolved symbiotically.</p> <p>This revolutionary understanding altered our perception of microbes. It would now seem inevitable that they influence us to an extent previously unimaginable. Richard Dawkins famously applied the following analogy to the relationship between genes and organisms in his book The Selfish Gene:</p> <p>“We are survival machines — robot vehicles blindly programmed to preserve the selfish molecules known as genes”. Perhaps, a similar analogy could be applied to the relationship between microbes and its host.</p> <h2 id="what-do-gut-bacteria-do">What do gut bacteria do?</h2> <p>Microbes have a wide variety of effects on its host. Some effects have even proven to be structural, aiding the development of organs. Others assist our metabolism or even protect us from pathogens. New research introduces the concept of microbes affecting our nervous system - ultimately altering our state of mind. Studies on the topic are constantly emerging and microbes will prove to interact with us in ways previously inconceivable.<br/> <img class="fig" src="https://2019.igem.org/wiki/images/7/7e/T--Lund--euprymna_scolopes.png" alt=""/></p> <p id="Euprymna" class="fig">Euprymna scolopes has an organ which growth is dependent on the presence of a special luminous bacteria. The organ illuminates the squids bottom, confusing predators on the hunt. Photo: Chris Frazee and Margaret McFall-Ngai ## Today's market of probiotics The main focus of the probiotic market is currently on gut flora. Having a poor gut microbiome entails health issues such as poor digestion, poor metabolism, an increased risk of heart disease and many more. Improving your gut microbiome would therefore prove extremely beneficial for your health, something companies quickly realised. What they didn’t realise was the complexity and intricacy of the several millions of interactions our microbiome has. This ultimately led to the demise of the reputation of probiotics as many of the promised effects were barely noticeable or even non-existent. New companies focus on research-based formulas in a means to salvage the reputation of probiotics. As more research emerges, it seems clear to us that an unhealthy microbiome is a contributor to many diseases which prove detrimental for our health. Therefore, supplementing, altering or modifying the microbiome for the better could be a key factor in treating many of those diseases in a sustainable and effective way. Using solutions brought on by nature itself is often proven to be the most viable alternative, however, slight modifications for the better could improve on nature’s own system even more. <h2 id="our focus">Our focus</h2> </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="synthetic"/><category term="biology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Written for iGEM]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bioterrorism in light of SARS-Cov-2</title><link href="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/bioterror/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bioterrorism in light of SARS-Cov-2"/><published>2019-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/bioterror</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/bioterror/"><![CDATA[<p>Technological advancement, novel scientific discoveries and innovations inherently bring the opportunity to act against the welfare of intelligent life. Some innovations bear only minimum risk with a low potential for disaster, but some innovations are highly riskful and have to be dealt with delicately in order to reduce the risk for malicious use. The assessment of risk is weighed against the potential benefits new innovations bring in order to evaluate if research can be continued ethically. In most cases, the continuation of research is certain, as in the development of new methods for cancer therapy. However, some research has notoriously been advocated against by the public and academia, such as the development of nuclear weapons, where we today unanimously realize that the benefits did not outweigh the risks, and are facing the constant risk of annihilation because of it. Many are weary of the risks biotechnology brings, afraid of the sudden appearance of yet another threatening weapon of mass destruction - and rightfully so. If a deadly and contagious enough bioweapon were to be developed by in a lab with failing safety precautions or by bioterrorists, it may be the last innovation ever created.</p> <p>An analogy of the risks brought on by innovation are elegantly exercised in the vulnerable world hypothesis [1]. Here, all possible innovations, ideas and discoveries lie in an urn, in the form of balls, and the shade of the ball defines its risk for detrimental outcome. So far, we’ve drawn many white balls and only a few grey balls with low to moderate risks associated with them. However, when reaching down into the urn of innovation we’re always running the risk of picking a black ball - one that unfailingly results in the destruction of civilization. When considering the advancement in biotechnology, we must constantly keep in mind the possibility of drawing a black ball, and we must, to the best of our ability, try to predict the shade of the ball before it’s drawn, because once a ball is drawn, it cannot be put back.</p> <p>The shade of a ball isn’t only dependent on the damage a product of that innovation will result in, but also the availability of the product. An innovation with 100% certainty of killing 100 individuals isn’t a black ball in the urn of innovations since it doesn’t result in the destruction of civilization, although, if the product is unusually easy to create it could certainly be of a darker shade. Imagine what would occur if a bomb, say a bunker buster which has the capacity of destroying military bunkers (as fittingly hinted at by its name), could be created by putting a football in a trash can. This innovation is highly unlikely, but if true, tremendously dangerous - several times more dangerous than the innovation is today. This is both due to the ease of creating it but also due to the wide availability of footballs and trash cans. Similarly, the shade could be determined by the possible countermeasures towards the innovation. If a deadly virus which is countered by an already widespread vaccine would be created, the severity of that creation is much lesser than it would have been if the vaccine was unavailable.</p> <p>A black ball is certainly unwanted, however, not unimaginable, especially not in the realm of biotechnology. In light of the mitigating efforts in fighting Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-Cov-2), our capacities for fighting viral agents are indisputably limited. As described by Simon Tisdall in The Guardian our global planning for the prevention of the present disaster is leaderless, lacking and late [2]. Our global and national infrastructure is failing to deal with the vast amount of Covid-19 cases, wreaking havoc both locally, in the form of lacking hospital beds and respirators, as well as unemployment, and globally, in the form of economic downfall. SARS-Cov-2 was most likely the result of animal wet-markets in Wuhan, China, where many species of live or freshly slaughtered animals are kept in near proximity, however, many conspiracies have risen regarding the origin [3]. Some believe that the virus was created in a laboratory outside of Wuhan, and wasn’t the result of cross-species contamination but of scientific endeavours. I certainly don’t condone the spread nor the validation of such unlikely speculations, however, the concept of creating a virus in a lab isn’t science fiction but is in fact widely applied in synthetic biology and other genetic engineering-practices. Although it wasn’t the case for this virus, the current outbreak should invite us to consider the possibility of a synthetic virus created with malevolent intent.</p> <p>Such a virus has been created before, although not with malevolent intent, and was a result of experimentation on the H5N1-virus (commonly known as the bird flu) in 2011. The researchers wanted to investigate if the highly deadly virus (with a mortality rate of up to 60%) could mutate in nature to become more contagious in mammals, and did so by genetic engineering [4, 5]. Successfully, they created a more contagious version of the virus which was capable of airborne transmission between mammals, and were later heavily criticized due to their lack of ethical consideration before conducting the research. The steadily increasing capabilities researchers posses in the realm of genetic engineering suggests that if such experiments were conducted in 2011, the availability of similar studies are significantly greater today. Similarly, the forthcoming of novel biohacking communities and the growth of the already existing ones, suggests that not only is the technical availability greater, but also subject to greater risk of realization.</p> <p>This is seemingly a recipe for disaster - a cry for a black ball in the urn of innovations. The wide availability, weak countermeasures and severe impact results in a doomsday machine, counting down the days until disaster. Luckily, established communities such as The International Genetically Modified Machine (iGEM) have policies and rules against potentially hazardous research, and ensure that all members undergo thorough considerations regarding the safety as well as the ethics of their projects [6]. Although these countermeasures could be regarded as weak, since they only affect the members of single communities, and aren’t strictly enforceable. Luckily, one would need to have a rather advanced insight into the science of genetic engineering to be able to create a deadly bioweapon, insight which is often connected to academia and regulated institutions. Although one can, with some certainty, conclude that as research continues to ease the way in which to biohack, the practice of genetic engineering will seep out of the realm of academia and into the hands of amateur practitioners. Let’s hope that your crazy, paranoid and doomsday-evoking neighbour down the street doesn’t get her hands on a viral agent and a biohacking-kit.</p> <p>SynthEthics will continue to investigate the ethical implications of advancement in synthetic biology and genetic engineering as well as the possibility of bioweapons and malicious research.</p> <ul> <li>[1] Bostrom N., “The Vulnerable World Hypothesis” 11-2019, Taken from [internet]: https://nickbostrom.com/papers/vulnerable.pdf</li> <li>[2]Tisdall S., The Guardian “Leaderless, lacking and late: a global plan to fight coronavirus is desperately needed” 04-2020 Taken from [internet]: https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/apr/11/leaderless-lacking-and-late-a-global-plan-to-fight-coronavirus-is-desperately-needed</li> <li>[3] Woodward A., Business Insider. “Both the new coronavirus and SARS outbreaks likely started in Chinese ‘wet markets.’ Historic photos show what the markets looked like” 02-2020 Taken from [internet]: .https://www.businessinsider.com/wuhan-coronavirus-chinese-wet-market-photos-2020-1?r=US&amp;IR=T</li> <li>[4] Herfst S, Schrauwen EJ, Linster M, et al. “Airborne transmission of influenza A/H5N1 virus between ferrets” 06-2012, Taken from [internet] https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4810786/</li> <li>[5] Committee on Science, Technology, and Law; Policy and Global Affairs; Board on Life Sciences; Division on Earth and Life Studies; Forum on Microbial Threats; Board on Global Health; National Research Council; Institute of Medicine. Perspectives on Research with H5N1 Avian Influenza: Scientific Inquiry, Communication, Controversy: Summary of a Workshop. Washington (DC): National Academies Press (US); 2013 Apr 4. Appendix C, The Two Published H5N1 Papers. Available from :https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK206985/</li> <li>[6] International Genetically Engineered Machine (iGEM) Safety, Taken 05-2020 from [internet]: https://2020.igem.org/Safety</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="synthetic"/><category term="biology"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="risks"/><category term="bioterrorism"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[written for SynthEthics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Opportunities and risks of synthetic biology</title><link href="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/sb-opp-risks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opportunities and risks of synthetic biology"/><published>2019-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/sb-opp-risks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://erikhartman.github.io/blog/2019/sb-opp-risks/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Synthetic biology, the field of science where life is altered, modernized and reconditioned to fit the needs of today, is one of the fastest growing fields of research in the scientific community. Engineers and scientists come together to create unimaginable and awe-inspiring organic machines by simply modifying the genome of organisms in a methodical manner. But where is this research taking us? What ethical inquiries must we pose to ensure that our future isn’t ruined by our own achievements? What can we do to ensure that the research is used to maximize the goodness in the world, and not the opposite? These are questions we must answer before we continue our efforts to expand our grasp of a technology we may not be able to master.</em></p> <p>The modern era of biology has resulted in a novel field, synthetic biology, where life is engineered to suit the needs of our modern world. A standardized system of biological parts and methods has enabled engineers to create organisms with minimal effort, and it is only bound to get easier. Our rapid progression foresees a future where genetic code is transcribed, modified and produced by the common practitioner, a future where the opportunities for good are exceptional but the risk for peril inevitable. Referencing the MIT-professor Max Tegmark, synthetic biology is one of those things where it is best to get it right the first time, for there may be no second. Therefore, we must emphasize the importance of investigating and discussing the ethics, regulations and the future of synthetic biology in order to minimize the risk for disaster.</p> <p>What opportunities may synthetic biology bring? Perhaps a more appropriate question is what won’t synthetic biology be able to achieve? Pharmaceuticals and biofuels are likely the first areas where engineered biological organisms will conquer the contemporary prevalent methods. Antibiotics and fossil fuels have showcased a lack of sustainability and we’re therefore in need of a viable solution, something that biological organisms can achieve. But inventions like these are merely scraping the utmost surface of capabilities of synthetic biology, and I urge you to delve deeper into your imagination with me.</p> <p>Trees are wonderful creations. By adding nutrition, sunlight and carbon dioxide, they produce the most intricate and wondrous nanostructures - leaves. When the leaves fall during autumn we throw them away, and the intricate structures are gone to waste. What if we could engineer the genome of trees to grow structures which suit our needs? As autumn looms, we may be collecting computer chips, ready for use. This might seem far fetched, but hopefully it illustrates what the future of synthetic biology might hold. A world where the most absurd, bizarre and ridiculous imaginations become reality. However, there are many alternate realities where the obscure biological inventions don’t favor our wellbeing, as described in the following vignette.</p> <p>In your workspace there is an ordinarily-looking printer. The printer is common amongst your contemporaries and prints both ink and biological structures. A recent jogging-incident has resulted in a nasty wound-infection on your heel and you decide to treat it with a bacteria which identifies the bacteria responsible for the infection and produces specific compounds to combat it. You google your local pharmacy, enter your unfortunate accident and they provide you with a link to download. You download a genetic sequence which codes for the bacterial genome and send it to your printer, and the bacteria are readily produced. You apply the bacterial solution to your wound and one day later, the infection is gone. The next day you check your email and find one from the local pharmacy, providing you with another link to download. Odd, they never email! You press the link and the printer starts buzzing. Later that day, your town is awfully silent and panic has struck the outside world. The genetic sequence you’ve downloaded carried a deadly, airborne and malicious virus, created by a terrorist group.</p> <p>To avoid a permanent eradication of intelligent life on earth it is important for us to consider the regulations, laws and directives which need to be implemented in our future society. We must find a perfect balance between hindering the development of malevolent research and restricting honest and legitimate scientific research. To do so, we must identify what research leads to biological weapons of mass destruction and what research leads to the thriving of mankind. It is therefore infinitely important for scientists, philosophers, economists, politicians and engineers to cooperate in the endeavor of discovering what moral boundaries these laws should comply with.</p> <p>Today’s state of regulations on synthetic biology is scattered and incoherent whilst also being overly restrictive and too loosely enforced. The US and the EU has dealt well with the biotechnological research of the 00’s and 10’s however, an overmounting amount of research is going to leave the current state of the European and US-legislation at a loss of words. The scientific community is working fast, and the jurisdictional community therefore needs to be three steps ahead when producing regulations. Envisioning what the future might hold and how our ethics is structured is therefore a necessity when constructing the regulations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="synthetic"/><category term="biology"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="risks"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[article for iGEM]]></summary></entry></feed>